<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An apologie or defence agaynst the calumnacion of certayne men which preferring wylfull wyll and carnal reason before the playn trueth of Gods gospel, (do sclaundre those men, which for the better seruinge of God with a more pure conscience, according to his holy word) haue abandoned theyr liuinges and vocacion, abydinge as exyles in poore estate oute of theyr natyue cou[n]trye.</title>
            <author>I. T., fl. 1555.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1555</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 35 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A13311</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 23619</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S103238</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99838995</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99838995</idno>
            <idno type="VID">3388</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A13311)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 3388)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1222:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An apologie or defence agaynst the calumnacion of certayne men which preferring wylfull wyll and carnal reason before the playn trueth of Gods gospel, (do sclaundre those men, which for the better seruinge of God with a more pure conscience, according to his holy word) haue abandoned theyr liuinges and vocacion, abydinge as exyles in poore estate oute of theyr natyue cou[n]trye.</title>
                  <author>I. T., fl. 1555.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[22] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>H. Singleton?],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Wesel? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1555.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Addressed to the reader on leaf A2r by: I. T.</note>
                  <note>Place of publication and printer suggested by STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A B⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Protestants --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Church history --  16th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:3388:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3388:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>¶ An Apolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie or defence agaynſt the calumnacion of cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne men, which preferring wylfull wyll and carnal reaſon before the playn trueth of Gods goſpel, (do ſclaundre thoſe men, which for the better ſeruinge of God with a more pure conſcience, according to his holy word) haue abandoned theyr liuinges and vocacion, abydinge as exyles in poore eſtate oute of theyr natyue cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trye. ☞</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>¶ Exodi .xxxiij.</bibl>
               <p>☞ O Lord let our hartes euermore ioye in thy teſtimonies, folowe not the multitude to doe euyll.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>¶ Pſalm .lxxiij.</bibl>
               <p>☞ Lyke as when a man waketh there re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayneth nothing of his ſlepe, (how pleaſaunt ſoeuer it was to the ſleper.) So ſhall there be nothing left of theyr Goddes. Where through they thought the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues happy in this worlde. But thou (O Lord) ſhalt rather make eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theyr pictures to be abhorred of eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye man in the Cytie.</p>
            </q>
            <p>¶ 1555.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:3388:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3388:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>The mercy and fauour of God oure heauenly father, pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed to vs by the merites of our Sauiour Chriſte. Communicated to vs by his holy ſpirite. I. T. Wiſheth to the gentle Reader.</head>
            <p>THe thing that moued me to vndertake, to au<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſwere this ſclau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dre (good frende) was not. That I either thought or iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged my ſelf ſo wyſe or ſo learned, as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> I could ſet it forth with ſuch wyſdom, or eloquenche: as ſo good a matter, and trewe cauſe requyred, or as yf ſome learned ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> had vndertaken it: neyther do I write it, to thende it ſhould be comen and receyued of all men, or haue free acceſſe into all places: but onelye to you my frend: and to that towne where ye pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently habyte (the place of my birth and educa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion.) As alſo for the excuſe of thoſe good m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r, of that towne, whiche in lyke maner with me haue abandoned &amp; geuen ouer theyr rowmes, which men as in Greke and Latyn auctours they be ignoraunt. By reaſon whereof, they ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not explicate nor make knowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to you, the cauſe why they haue choſen this paynefull exyle: ſo they wiſhe you, and all other honeſte men, to know and vnderſtand: that neyther lightneſſe, raſhe wyll, or i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>conſtancie, hath moued them there vnto, (as ſome of that towne, vntruely &amp; agaynſt theyr owne knowledge doe ſurmyſe &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:3388:3"/>blowe abroa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e.) But a good zeale grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded vp on Gods trueth, confyrmed by the opinion of all good and godly learned men: and that they might with the more pure conſcience ſerue god in the congregacion of the godly, where Gods moſte holy worde and Sacramentes are pure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly preached and miniſtred. In the which place as the Prophete Dauid ſaythe: It is better to dwel in a moſt poore degree, then to abyde in wealth and proſperous eſtate, among the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked. Which mynd and good purpoſe of theirs, as a iuſte excuſe to ſatiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ye the mindes of good and godly men which principally they deſyre. They haue earneſtly deſyred me, to make kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen and to put forth the ſame in writinge: and to adreſſe this Apologie to you: Knowig right well, that although for lacke of learninge and wyſoom, I ſhall not be able to ſatiſfye theyr expectacion, or ſet it forth according to the wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thynes of the matter. For that I neuer haunted ſcoles or anye vniuerſities. Nor neuer was brought vp in any other ſtate then with them, as a moſt poore man and Souldiour, (ſimple and vnworthye) yet becauſe they ſhall aſwell perceyue my good wyll and preſte ſeruyce to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes them, as charitie and our conſuete fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliaritie woulde, and compelleth me: as alſo for that my parte is in it participating, the life obloque and ſclaundre with them. For that we haue wrought al one lyke facte, and attempted one entrepryſe. Theſe thinges wayed and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poned, I haue the more gladly graunted to ful fyll theyr requeſtes, praying you my frend of charitie to graunt me thus much fauour. That
<pb facs="tcp:3388:3"/>yf I ether ſhal write or pe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne any thig y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> agreeth not w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> your mind, &amp; the opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of other me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, not to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne it at the firſt ſight, becauſe it maketh not for your purpoſe, but rather co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>farre it w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcriptures of God, the trew touchſtone, which al me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s workes ought to be iudged by, &amp; to the which I pray you ſubmit your co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce: &amp; yf ye find y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it varie not fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſacred word of god, nor diſſent fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the mynde of good &amp; godly learned me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> embrace it as a manifeſt trueth, deſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring god y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> father of al mercy for his ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes ſake Chriſt, in the worke of his holi ſpirite, to make you conſent to it. And to teſtifye our doynges to be lawful and conſonante to Gods goſpell. Staying your opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with this our aunſwere putting other men to ſilence by the ſame.</p>
            <p>And now to come to the cauſes which ye pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>poned to me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in my houſe, ſaying: ye were ſente fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> many good honeſt &amp; godly me, which not a litle merueled, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I had ſet away into flau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ders my wife &amp; childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: &amp; much more that I my ſelf was alſo delibered to folow. Wherin, as ye al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged, they iudged I wrought vnwiſely &amp; not according to knowledge, but rather preferred a wil more wilful, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> godli wiſe, knowig aſwell my poore eſtate &amp; litle riches w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> my great fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, as alſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> inciuil nature of this nacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> finale relief, ſaying: w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>in a ſhort time begging to ouer take me, for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> I nether had arte, faculte, or occu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to liue by. More y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> if god ſhould tourne y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> impietie of this time, I ſhould neuer be able to recouer the like rowme or office, &amp; ſo al my life wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der in miſery, which they as my very fren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des much lame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted, with many other cauſes by you alledged, thereby to ſtaye my iourneye.
<pb facs="tcp:3388:4"/>Which perſwaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s as to the fleſhe, they ſemed harde and vneaſi to be borne, and tollerated of any worldly man. So I for my parte do moſte hartely praiſe God, whoſe good worke it was: they not abaſhed me nor altered my purpoſe, as ye my frende know right well.</p>
            <p>Secondlye ye alledged agaynſt me the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynges of other me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which ye named both good honeſt, and godly: and of an vpright pure con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, which men obſerued the ordre of thys tyme.</p>
            <p>Thyrdely ye ſayd that yf my co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience were ſo ſtrayght laced, as that I could not conſente, to the putting of my name into the boke among others, you for your parte iudged it no ſynne, nor felte any repugnau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of coſcience for your ſo doyng, whérby ye iudged it no offence. And yf it were ſinne, as ye ſayde ye doubted, yet it was a light ſynne, and eaſy to be forgeue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: God muſt remitte greater offences, or els ye ſhould neuer come in heauen.</p>
            <p>Well, now my frend accordinge to my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience &amp; little knowledge, receyued fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Gods word: I wyll aunſwere youre three cauſes al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged agaynſt me. Prayinge you to accept the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in as good parte, as with an vnfayned harte &amp; good mynde I doe adreſſe them to you.</p>
            <p>And as to the fyrſte cauſe which ye prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to ſtaye my goynge: whereas you &amp; manye good men lame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted that miſery ſhould oppreſſe me, and that ſpecially in a ſtraunge land farre fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> frendes. Where I ſhould be compelled ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to begge or labor, which I neuer had done nor was brought vp in ſuch extremitie, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb facs="tcp:3388:4"/>they feared I ſhould not be able to endure it. I aunſwere them with S. Paul, I haue lear<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned in what eſtate ſoeuer I am, there with to be content. I can doe all thinges thorough the helpe of Chriſt. I alſo ſaye with S. Paul,
<note place="margin">Phil. iiij. Rom. viij</note> ſhall tribulacion, or anguiſhe, or perſecucion: eyther hunger, or nakedneſſe: perill, or ſworde, ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate vs from the loue of God:
<note place="margin">Timo. vi Mar. viij</note> More the ſame Apoſtle ſayth: Godlines is great ryches, yf a man be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t with that he hath, for we brought nothing into the world, and it is a playne caſe, that we can carye nothing out. What ſhould it auayle a man to winne the whole world, &amp; loſe his owne ſoule: I moſt hartely reioyſe in god, that I haue not receyued his goſpell in vayne. For I had rather with Lazarus enioy a poore eſtate,
<note place="margin">Luke. xvi</note> begging my bread in myſerye w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a quiet co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience: the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with dyues to wallow in welth, and for pleaſure ſake loſe the lyfe euerlaſting. Chriſt Ieſus the alone Sauiour,
<note place="margin">Philip. ij.</note> our Lorde &amp; mayſter, thought it no robberye, as S. Paule ſayth, beyng very God, to take our nature vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him, and for our ſakes to become man in moſte lowe degree. Who as a moſt pure pater<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> and godly example for vs to folow, walked in this vale of miſerie, in great humilitie and poore e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, ſaying: y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> foxes haue holes,
<note place="margin">Luke. ix</note> &amp; the byrdes of the ayre haue neſtes: but the ſonne of man hath not a place to put his head in. O my frend theſe places of Scripture are not written in vayne, but for our learninge:
<note place="margin">Roma. x<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> that we through pacience and comforte of the Scripture might haue hope. It is geuen vs as S. Paule ſayth: not onely to beleue on Chriſt: but to ſuffre for
<pb facs="tcp:3388:5"/>his ſake, yf Chriſt Ieſus my Lord and maiſter walked in ſuch poore eſtate, Wall I a wretched ſinner, beyng but earth &amp; wormes meat, hauig no certe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tie of my life,
<note place="margin">Rom. viij ij. Tim. 7.</note> for a litle pleaſure in this worlde loſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> life euerlaſting<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> God forbid, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bring y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> yf we wil raigne w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Chriſt, we muſt ſuffre w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> him. Now my fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de yf I &amp; other men ſhould doe as you &amp; other do, what nede we to ſuffre w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> chriſt: For yf, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> goſpel by god his ſpecial mercy, &amp; auctoritie of the king is ſet forth, I the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> embrace it as a truth in thoſe daies there is no cauſe why I ſhould ſuffre for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, as in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> time of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> godly Price king Toward y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſixt.
<note place="margin">Pſal. lxvi Gapien. 3 Lccleſi. 2</note> But whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for our vntha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kefulnes &amp; wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched liuing, god doth take his goſpel away fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs, as it is come to paſſe in our la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d at this day, to make trial of his elect according to this ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: As gold is tried in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> furneys, ſo god doth trie his elect, yf I then (as you &amp; moſt men doe now i theſe daies) diſſemble w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> trueth, which before I embraſed, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>firming my ſelfe to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piete of this time. There is the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> no cauſe why I ſhould ſuffre w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> chriſt, no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wil lay any mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to my charge, yf externally I obſerue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> law, and the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> were theſe wordes of ſuffring w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> chriſt in vayn, &amp; the goſpel ſuch a trueth as I liſte to make &amp; applie it. Yf I ſhal perſwade my ſelf to pleaſe chriſt, &amp; to be in fauor w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> God, &amp; yet wil not ſuffre w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> chriſt. My fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de in mine opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it is not in our choſe, to take vp chriſtes croſſe as we lift, &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> way we would: but as god our he a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly father in chriſt hath deſtined &amp; appointed vs vnto: wel, let y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be ware which obſerueth the ordre of this time, maynteyninge his owne doyng, &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ning other me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for not doyng the
<pb facs="tcp:3388:5"/>ſame, &amp; yet wil ſay: he is gods ſeru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>t. Truely I wil not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne hi, for God ſhal be his iudge: But ſurely I thinke he might aſwell ſaye there were no god, for god is none otherwiſe knowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; honored of him, but as his fleſhly wyll liſt to knowe &amp; ſerue him, not captiuating his iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> word of god, by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which word god is truly ſerued &amp; worſhipped &amp; not pleaſed as we imagine.
<note place="margin">Mat. xvij</note> We are co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded to harke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> voyce of chriſt &amp; to heare him, which ſayth: he y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wyll be my diſciple let him forſake himſelfe, &amp; take vp his croſſe &amp; folow me. Now yf y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which wil liue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> al ſecurite &amp; pleaſure of this life, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God maketh trial of his church, wil nether ſuf<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fre w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> him,
<note place="margin">Mat. xvi.</note> nor take vp his croſſe &amp; folow him &amp; yet wil ſay he hath right in his doyng, ſurelye this place may be verified of him. Not al they which ſay, lord, lord ſhal entre into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kingdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,
<note place="margin">Iames .i. Roma. ij.</note> but he y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> doeth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wil of my father which is in heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hearers of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> law, but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> doers ſhalbe iuſtified. Chriſt ſayth: Zroade is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> way that leadeth to deſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; many go in therat, but narow is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> way y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ledeth to ſaluacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,
<note place="margin">Mat. vij. Luke. xiij</note> &amp; few ther be which find it. Chriſtes flock is b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle flock. The cauſe my fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, why it is but litle &amp; the narrow way not fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de out, is: becauſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> of our nature we are ſinful, &amp; delight in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion thereof, pleaſing our ſelues w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> corruptible thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges, not delighting in heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly miſteries, for fleſh &amp; bloud is not capable of heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>lye know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge. Therefore hath God geuen vs ouer to a lewde mynd, perſwading oure ſelues to be in the righte, when as manifeſtlye we are in the wro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g, according to the ſaying of S. Paul,
<note place="margin">Roma. i.</note> whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as they knewe God &amp; dyd not worſhip him an god, the lord gaue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ouer to their own luſtes
<pb facs="tcp:3388:6"/>And becauſe that whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we had y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> light of Gods Goſpel among vs, we embraced not, nor wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked in the ſame. Therefore hath God ſuffered darkenes &amp; errour to ouerwhelme vs: &amp; yet we wyll ſaye, we are in the right, &amp; may diſſemble for the time, ſaying: God knoweth our hartes. My frende be not deceyued: God requyreth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whole ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> withall our powers to ſerue him ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the fyrſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundemente,
<note place="margin">Exod. xx. Mat. xxij.</note> where it is writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Thou ſhalte loue the Lorde thy God withal thy harte, ſoule, &amp; mynd, &amp; withall thy powers. How we obſerue this precepte when as we proſtrate our ſelues before an Idol par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking with the vngodly: the Lorde at the laſt day ſhal reuele &amp; make openly knowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. It is like as yf a maried woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhould ſubmit her body to the vſe of another ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: &amp; when her huſbande layeth the offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to her charge, ſhe au<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſwereth: huſband be not angrie for my ſo doyng, for al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though I abandoned my body to that ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s vſe yet I reſerued my hart wholy to you. My fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d I thinke there is no man, beynge of any godly knowledge, could digeſt that aunſwere of his wyfe, or take it in good parte: but condemning her as an aduoutreſſe would repudiat and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake her. And ſhal we perſwade oure ſelues to pleaſe God,
<note place="margin">Exod. xx. Deut. vi.</note> beyng a ialouſe God (as the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture calleth him) who requyreth of vs y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whole man to ſerue him withal: when as we geue the greater parte of his creacion to the ſeruinge of Idols, ſaying: God knoweth &amp; hath my harte. Well God deale w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> vs according to his greate mercy, &amp; geue vs an hart to repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t &amp; knowledge our offences, leaſt we periſhe in our ſinnes: for
<pb facs="tcp:3388:6"/>as God is mercyful, ſo is he iuſt. Chriſt ſaith:
<note place="margin">Luk. xiiij Math. x. Luke. ix.</note> he that ſetteth more by father or mother, wife, childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, landes, riches, or cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tryr, then by me, is not mete for me, nor worthye to be my diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. Reade the whole Chap. in Luke, &amp; examen what the buylding of the towre ſignifieth. Ye haue heard often taught &amp; preached, that, he y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wyl profeſſe the Goſpel in tyme of proſperitie ſhould caſt accompt w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> him ſelf, what may hap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pen to him for the ſame, in the dayes of aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie. Or els in vayne hath he begon to buy lde, and ſhalbe called a fooliſhe buylder. I thinke there be a great many of honeſt &amp; good men in that towne, which in times paſt haue bene fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent Goſpellers, and yet at this daye loue the trueth, ſorowing in their hartes the impiete of this tyme. That yf it were not for feare to loſe theyr liuinges, riches, &amp; countrie: &amp; to become poore in a ſtraunge land, would folowe &amp; ſeke Chriſt in the wildernes:
<note place="margin">Apoca. xij</note> ſearching with paine to ſeke out the narowe way. But alas ſo colde is oure loue to Chriſte, which hath ſo dearelye bought vs, that we could be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tent to loue him ſo that we loſe not by him. But theſe doubtes to taſt miſerie, poull vs from folowing poore Chriſt. So frayle is our lyfe, &amp; ſuch a lumpe of ſynne &amp; corrupte tabernacle, we are wrapped in. That ſeyng the beſt waye &amp; knowing y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter parte, we can not chuſe it, nor walke in the ſame. I pray God this ſentence be not verified vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs.
<note place="margin">Luke. xij</note> He that knoweth his mayſters wyll &amp; doeth it not, ſhalbe beaten with many ſtrypes. By many tribulacions muſt we entre into the Kingdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Chriſt ſayth:
<note place="margin">Luke. ix.</note> he that putteth
<pb facs="tcp:3388:7"/>his hand to the plough, &amp; loketh backe, is not mete for the kingdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.
<note place="margin">mat. 24. x.</note> It is not y<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough for vs to haue begon in the knowledge of Chriſt, oneles we perſeuer &amp; folowe him to the end. Cloſing our dayes in his peace, which peace of Chriſt is better in a beggers boſome, at the howre of death, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a mountayn of gold to a ryche ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with a troubled conſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. Chriſt ſayth: my ſhepe heare my voyce: now my fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, becauſe the voyce of oure ſhepeherde Chriſt,
<note place="margin">Iohn. x.</note> is not to be heard in that towne where ye dwell. Therefore I &amp; other men of that place, haue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandoned our lyuinges &amp; vocacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to ſeke oure ſhepeherd chriſt that we might heare his voice and participate his ſacramentes purely mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred according to his holy worde, &amp; in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> place to our great comforte to prayſe him: where, to our great conſolacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we now remayne. In the which companie how ioyfull it is to be amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g. The Prophete Dauid deſcribeth in the lxxxiiij Pſalm,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 84.</note> which I moſt hartely requyre you, not onely to reade, but diligentlye to marke &amp; exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min, what the Prophete meaneth in the ſame, &amp; by th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> place to iudge whether we haue righte in our doyuges, or are iuſtely to be conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ned, O my frend in that towne where ye preſentely inhabite, the goſpel of Ieſus Chriſt hath bene moſte plenteouſly preached &amp; purely taught y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpace of ſeuen yeares.
<note place="margin">Mat. xiij. Mar. iiij.</note> And yf there ſhoulde no good grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d appeare after ſo much &amp; long ſow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge of ſo good ſede, to bring forth encreaſe of good corne, it mighte well be called a curſed place, &amp; an yll ſoyle. I ſaye this my frend, yf al me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of that town, which were called goſpellers
<pb facs="tcp:3388:7"/>ſhould obſerue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ordre of this vnhappye tyme, ſubmitting the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues to this vngodly religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. What a cauſe of triumphe ſhould the papiſtes haue to reioyſe: perſwadig &amp; blowing abrode no trueth or religion to be trew, but onely that which they now teache &amp; ſet forth, becauſe all me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> obſerue the ſame. But for becauſe they ſee a nou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bre of good &amp; godly learned me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the loſſe of their liues, &amp; ſpilling of their bloud, to teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fye it an vntruth. As alſo a great nou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bre of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of good co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerſacion doe departe theyr countrey, leauing their riches &amp; liuinges: ſome of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> beginneth to doubt, whether his religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be a truth or not. Other which are of the worſt ſorte of papiſtes, &amp; that moſt ſetteth forth this religion, be aſhamed to make greate boaſte of their doctrine: for that in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tyme of the goſpel, lyke diſſemblers &amp; hipocrites, they gaue place to the trueth, and would in no wyſe ſuffre for theyr religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And nowe they ſeing men to dye and ſuffre penurie in a ſtrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge land, it maketh them poul back their to much boaſting of their religion, ſo that by this meanes it appeareth moſt playne to him that hath but halfe an eye, that the goſpel is a moſte manifeſte trueth and pure religion, in that men ſuffre for the ſame, which is promyſed to all them,
<note place="margin">ij. Tim. i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> that wyll lyue godly in Chriſt Ieſu. Theſe cauſes my frend &amp; many other, moued me with other me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to vnder take this painful iourney, &amp; greuous exyle. Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amen the boke of geneſis, &amp; po<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der wel y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> doyng of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> old Patriarke Iacob, who forſoke no ſmale ſubſtau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce &amp; riches beſide y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> comodite of his cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trey &amp; dwelling place,
<note place="margin">Gene. 43.</note> onli as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcripture ſayth
<pb facs="tcp:3388:8"/>Becauſe of famyne that occupied y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſoyle and land where he dwelte, and in much payne and great trauayle in his olde dayes w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a greate fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milie drew into Egipte, a people in maners &amp; condicions, not agreeyng with his nature. Yf our father Iacob dyd vndertake this long and painful iourney, to ſeke meate for the body: co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidre my frend, how much more we that are cal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>led Chriſtians, &amp; which haue profeſſed Chriſt, ought to ſeke for the fode of the ſoule, which is the preaching of Gods holi word &amp; participa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion of his holy Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes: by the which we waxe ſtrong in fayth, pacience, &amp; all good wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes,
<note place="margin">Mat. iiij.</note> as Chriſt our mayſter ſayth: Man ſhal not lyue by bread only, but by euery worde y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedeth oute of the mouth of God. Chriſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundeth by Eſay the Prophet,
<note place="margin">Eſay. lij.</note> ſaying to his people: Away, away, get you out from thence, and touche no vncleane thing. Ieremie in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther place cryeth,
<note place="margin">Ierem. li.</note> ſaying: Flee away from Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilon, euery man ſaue his lyfe. O my frend do ye thinke that the word of the ſpirite of God, ſpeaking ſo earneſtly &amp; with ſuch vehemence, by the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nouthes of thoſe holy men: to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de vs to auoyde the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany of Idolaters, is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in vayne &amp; to no purpoſe. Truely in my ſim<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple iudgement, &amp; as my conſcience teſtifieth to me (ruled by Gods holy ſpirite) They ar writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten ſpecially for our dayes, that we ſhoulde be without al excuſe, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as God ſhal lay &amp; make open euery mans dedes.
<note place="margin">ij. Cor. vi.</note> S. Paul hath the lyke ſaying: Come out fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> amonge them, &amp; ſeparate your ſelues fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them, ſaith the Lord: reade out the Chap. and note the wordes well. And lette
<pb facs="tcp:3388:8"/>your conſcience witneſſe with you, who hath y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> right. It is a thig very difficile to touche pitch,
<note place="margin">Eccl. xiij.</note> and not to be defyled. I wylknitte vp the firſt parte of your matter obiected againſt me with this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cluſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. The. viij. Chap. to the Romains, and ſo conſequentely all the whole Scripture through, doth teache theſe two poinctes. That fyrſt, God the father in his free mercy by hy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſonne Chriſt hath choſen vs, withoute any de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruing on oure partes, accordinge to this ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge: Thoſe which he appoynted before, them alſo he called: &amp; which he called, them alſo he iuſtified: which he iuſtified, them alſo he glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifyed. Secondly, he dyd it to this ende: that as the ſcripture ſayth: they might be made like to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Image of his ſonne, in ſuffring with him. Now my fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, yf we wil perſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ade our ſelfes, to be choſen in Chriſt: and wyl not ſuffre with him, and yet thinke to raygne with him. I pray God we beguyle not our ſelues.</p>
            <p>To come to the ſecond part, In that ye layd agaynſte me the doynges of other men, which being both good and godlye obſerued the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of this tyme. Laying to my charge, why I ſhoulde be more precyſe and ſcrupule of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, then other men they beyng godly.</p>
            <p>To that ſayinge I aunſwere. The doynges of men, is no preſidente for a Chriſten man to folowe, how good ſoeuer they be called, onles they dyrecte theyr wayes, according to Gods holy worde. Howbeit folowing the counſayle of S. Paule. I wyll reporte well of them, as Chriſten charitie, woulde to iudge the beſte in hid thinges. Therfore for that I can not know
<pb facs="tcp:3388:9"/>with what mynd they do it, I muſte folow the admonicio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the Apoſtle, to thinke wel of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Onely this I know, &amp; am not ignoraunte of, &amp; by experience do proue &amp; taſte in my fraile life and corrupt nature (which is altogether ſinne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful) that terrour of lawes maketh vs to ſtoupe and decline to thinges, ſinning agaynſt know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, for the preſeruacion of this vncertayne life, &amp; keping of our goodes. O that we would remembre this ſaying:
<note place="margin">i. Petri. i.</note> All fleſhe is as graſſe, &amp; all the glorie of man is as the flowre of graſſe, which ſentence wel wayed would kepe vs fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> diſſembling in that thing whereof our co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce accuſeth vs: &amp; to the which my harte in no wiſe can agree to conſent.
<note place="margin">Mat. xvi.</note> Chriſt ſayeth: who ſoeuer ſhal loſe his life for my fake, ſhal find it. More I am a ialous God,
<note place="margin">Exod. xx.</note> that cannot ſuffre my ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to be geuen to any other, nor no part ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. The Lord in theſe wordes doeth accommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>date him ſelfe to vs, as oure weake nature can know him. Our fleſhe is in no one cauſe ſo ſone moued or prouoked to wrath, as in that fighte that may ſtyrre vs to ialowſye, which offence we can almoſt by no interceſſion or ſute ſkant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly remitte or pardon. And God which ſeeth al our doynges, &amp; before whoſe preſece al thiges are open, beholdeth howe we diſſemble w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hys loue makinge familiar fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dſhip &amp; league w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his enemies. Wel theſe wordes I am a ialous god, require in vs an vpright pure, vndefiled couer ſacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, leſt by our diſſimulacion we prouoke the lord to anger.
<note place="margin">i. Petri. i.</note> O my frend y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> god which in hys mercy hath ſo dearely bought vs (not with cor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ruptible gold or ſyluer, but with his moſte ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly &amp; precious harte bloud, requyreth of vs our whole ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> mind &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerſacion to ſerue him,
<pb facs="tcp:3388:9"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ccording to this ſaying: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e holy,
<note place="margin">Leuit. xix i. Petri. 1. ij. Cori. vi</note> for I am ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>: be not partakers with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vngodly: for what <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ncorde hath Chriſt with Belial <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> or howe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>reeth darkenes with light: Now thy frende <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>amen theſe wordes well, &amp; iudge whether it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e the acte or parte of him, that would <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e repu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d &amp; taken for a perfect Chriſten man, to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>unicáte &amp; be partaker with ydolaters, and to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ire his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e into the boke among them, to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>reat ſclaundre of Gods Goſpell. In that the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>apiſtes may triumphe, that all me (and ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lly ſuch as were called Feruent goſpellers) do <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mbrace and folow the order of this vnhappy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>yme: whereby they boaſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> &amp; glorie their reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ion to be moſt trew. On the other part, conſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e how ye wound &amp; offende the conſcience of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>our weake brother, not yet growen to ful per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ection of knowledge, who hath his eyes open <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pon you, who ſeyng you to do the ſame, thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eth it a lawful acte, &amp; ſo ye are the cauſe of his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>all. S. Paul ſayth: when ye ſinne agaynſt the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rethren, &amp; wounde their weake conſcience,
<note place="margin">i. Cor. viij</note> ye finne agaynſt Chriſt. Reade the Chapt. yf S. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aul had that mynde in lawfull thinges: that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ather then he would offend the conſcience of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>is weake brother, he woulde neuer <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ate fleſhe while he liued, how much more my fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ought <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e to haue a conſcience to offend your brother, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n an vnlawefull thinge: We be to him ſayeth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hriſt: that offendeth one of theſe little ones. It were better for him to haue a mylſtone tied <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t his necke, &amp; ſo caſt into the ſea.
<note place="margin">Luk. xvij.</note> Cal to youre remembraunce, &amp; digeſt well the worthy com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendacion geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to Elea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in Gods boke cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
<pb facs="tcp:3388:10"/>the Bible. That were as his fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des moue with peuiſhe pitie (hauinge no taſte of an vp right conſcience) perſwaded him for the ſau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> garde of his lyfe to eate ſwynes fleſhe,
<note place="margin">2. Mac. 6</note> whic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in no wiſe he would do, for that it was again<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the law<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of God, &amp; his conſcience. And wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> his frendes perceyned that for no perſwaſio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> he would not eate it, they earneſtly oportun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> and counſayled him to make a countenau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> though he had eaten ſome, which diſſimulaci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Ele<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>azar knowing it to be againſt Gods wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> aſwel fearing the yll preſident &amp; example, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> might grow thereof to other men: beyng yo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> weake, and vnperfect in Gods worde, as al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> remembring his honorable lyfe, good conue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſacion &amp; old age, would in no caſe make coun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> nannce to eate, nor vſe any ſuch diſſimulacio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> but rather preſar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed to dye, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he would co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> terfect ſuche hypoc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iſie. Loke &amp; reade the ter<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> calling for wyſoo &amp; knowledge to God. Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to the boke with a pure my<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>de, &amp; ye ſha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> eaſely perceaue, whether the obſeruers of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> tyme walke in that puritie of lyfe, whiche <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>fely requyr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d in him, that in time paſt ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> bene called a goſpeller. There is another no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and leſſon in Eleagar to be marked<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> his frendes pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aiued the conſtancie and pu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> mynde of him that he would in no caſe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to theyr perſwaſions &amp; counſayl: they conu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted theyr amytis<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> &amp; frandyſhip into malice. S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> yf that El<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ar had conſented to that unpiet<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> they had had a goodly cloſe to maynteyne a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> coloure theyr between to be good, with thy ſaying: Lo, ſuch a man doth diſſemble, who
<pb facs="tcp:3388:10"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oth good &amp; learned: and ſo they woulde haue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uſtifyed theyr doynges to be lawefull by hy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> example: which Elear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ercey<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing, conſtant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y to the death, withſtode that coloured conſci<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ence, and vnpure mynde of theyrs. My frende I wryte this becauſe ſome men of that towne wyll reporte euyll of me and other men which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e gone awaye, not for that they can laye anye wictedneſſe or vngodlye conuerſacion to oure charge (God be glorified therefore,) but only of an yll mynd: becauſe we wyl not conſente to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>heyr doynges, and ioyne with them in obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>inge the ordre of this religion. Well, let them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ay what they lift.
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> God from whom no ſecrete <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s hyd, &amp; which knoweth the hartes of al men, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>an iudge with what conſcience we haue aban<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>doned our vocacions, &amp; countrey: &amp; howe glad we would be to haue theyr good wyl &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>acion, doyng alſo as they d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, ſo we knew and were aſſured to pleaſe god. But thus much for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n aunſwere to the ſecond poyn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>: I woulde yf <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> pleaſed God, I had ſufficient learning and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ype knowledge in his holy word,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> by the ſame <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o argue their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oynges. But this much I write and thinke, that yf they be good men fearinge God, and of a good conſcience, as ye ſaye they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e, which obſerue the ordre of this ty<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e, (and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rnely I thinke they be ſo a greate noumbre of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hem,) then I ſay they haue a pricke of conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſtifyeth to them, theyr doynges <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o be vnlawfull. And which before God with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eares and ſorowe of harte they doe dewayle,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ot ſtandinge in defence of theyr doynges, as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e my frende doe, which in my <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:3388:11"/>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>th agrauate<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the offence before God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> man.</p>
            <p>To aunſwere the thyrde poynte, in that y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> make it ſo facill and light, beleuing it to be no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſinne, ſaying<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> The Lorde muſt remitte greate<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> offences. Well, I pray God ye preſume not to<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> much in his mercy, for he is not mercy full, bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to them that repent, theyr wickedues. I coul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſomewhat more by the ſcriptures dilate &amp; ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proue the ſame, as vnlearned as I a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>but the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> fewe leaues areynoughe, to hym that hath <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> good conſcience<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> The Byble ſayeth there is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> waye which ſemeth right vnto a man, but th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ende of it leadeth to deſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.
<note place="margin">Deu. 5.12</note> Ye ſhall not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> euery one of you, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eth right in your owne eyes, but that which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>gumaund you, ſayeth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Lord: becauſe thy ſy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e is forgeuen thee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Be no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> therfore without<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>are,
<note place="margin">Eccleſi. v</note> neyther heap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> one ſynne vpon another. And ſaye not: tu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e the mercye of the Lorde is great: he ſhall for<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> geue me my ſinnes, be they neuer ſo many. Fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> lyke as he is merciful, ſo goeth wrath fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hyn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> alſo,
<note place="margin">Eſaye. v.</note> &amp; his indignacion cometh down vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſyn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s. Wo be to them, that call euyll good, and good euyll, which make, darkenes light, &amp; ligh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> darkenes: that make ſowre ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ete, and ſwet<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> ſowre. Now my frend, yf ye may doe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which ye co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mit without offence, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ye haue ſcriptur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to aſſure &amp; warrant youre d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ynge. Or els you nor no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ls, (be he neuer ſo wel learned) ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> defend the ſame, but to be ſinnefull. For ſain<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Paul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſay<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>h:
<note place="margin">Roma. 14</note> Whatſoeuer is not of faith, tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſame is ſynne. Reade the. x<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. and .xix. Pſalm o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Dauid, iudge your ſelfe by them. And wher<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:3388:11"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>wene ſinnes of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>. Kem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſau ſought <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eares, and found it not: Iuſti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, leaſt ye prouoke the Lord. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>.
<note place="margin">Lu. xviij.</note> The Publican confeſſinge his fawte <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>: but the Phariſe, iuſtifying him <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> was condemned. The Prophete Dauid <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſalmes deſy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eth God to par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> of thoſe which fall of frayltie, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> for vengeaunce, to fal vpon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>folde, which ſynne of obſtina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> I pray<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> God the father of al mercy, &amp; Lord <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> conſolacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for his mercy ſake in the bloud <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> his ſonne Chriſt, to make you withal them, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> in this tyme of imp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ete fall through frail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> and for feare <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f lawes in the noumbre of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> man, which<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> xxxij. Pſalm ſpeaketh of. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> thus an end<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> according to my one talente <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> Fare well in the Lorde Ieſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> withall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> that vnfay<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>edlye call vpon the name of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> Lorde.</p>
            <p>And thus my frende I ende this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ple wryting, praying<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>not to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> with the ſame. And yf ye <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> in it, whiche agreeth not with youre <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>nion, and wherein ye thinke I erre &amp; ſtraye <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> the ſcriptures, aduertyſe me <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>nd I ſhall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ſte gladly reuoke and recante the ſame. But <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> fynd that it agreewith the word of God, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> I pray you c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aſe to ſaye or thinke our do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> to be yll, beyng a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> &amp; aduocate for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> to all good men: which through ignoraunce <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> all ſineſterly reporte of our goynge awaye.
<pb facs="tcp:3388:12"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> quiet my conſcience;, and aſſure my <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> then the ſclaunde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>rous <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:3388:12"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
